Guide to the John R. Pierce Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John R. Pierce papers
1933-2002
1960-2002
SC0749
Pierce, John R. (John Robinson), 1910-2002
Pierce, John Robinson, 1910-2002
9 Linear feet
Papers include journals, 1986-1995; biographical and bibliographic materials; correspondence; typescripts of scholarly work, fiction and poetry; music manuscripts; published articles and books; research files; photographs; and other materials. The focus is primarily on his interest in computers and music and his authorship of science fiction stories, with a few published articles and photographs pertaining to the Echo satellite. Other items of note include the report on a visit to British electronics laboratories by J. R. Pierce and H. D. Hagstrum, 1944, and a transcript of a visit with H. G. Wells, 1944.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
John R. Pierce earned all three of his degrees at the California Institute of Technology: B.S. in 1933, M.S. in 1934, and Ph.D. in 1936. He worked at Bell Telephone Laboratories from 1936 to 1971, where his work included electronic tubes, microwave communications, and psychoacoustics. After leaving Bell, he joined the faculty at the California Institute of Technology where he taught until 1980 and was a chief technologist at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory from 1979 to 1982. In 1983 he became a visiting professor of music, emeritus, at the Center for Computer Research in Music and Acoustics at Stanford University. In addition to his scholarly work, Pierce wrote science fiction under the name of J. J. Coupling, as well as his own.
Description of the Collection
Papers include journals, 1986-1995; biographical and bibliographic materials; correspondence; typescripts of scholarly work, fiction and poetry; music manuscripts; published articles and books; research files; photographs; and other materials. The focus is primarily on his interest in computers and music and his authorship of science fiction stories, with a few published articles and photographs pertaining to the Echo satellite. Other items of note include the report on a visit to British electronics laboratories by J. R. Pierce and H. D. Hagstrum, 1944, and a transcript of a visit with H. G. Wells, 1944.
Access Terms
Borroff, Marie.; Pierce, John R. (John Robinson), 1910-2002; Wells, H. G. (Herbert George), 1866-1946.; Music --Acoustics and physics.; Science fiction, American.
Collection Contents
- Original Accession, Accesion ARCH-1999-306
  - Journal 1986 – 88 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Journal 1988 – 92 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Journal 1992 – 95 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Poems (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Music MSS c. 1936 – 37 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Borroff, Marie (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: re. Current Directions in Computer Music Research (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: re. “Periodicity and Pitch Perception” (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: re. “Computing Education” (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Noll, A. Michael (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Honorary degrees (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Telephone book (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photos (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Computer invoice (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Patent for Passive Non-Linear Filter, 1996-97 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Computers in Higher Education – Report, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gilbert, Steven – "Academic Software – Vision and Perspective; working paper March 15, 1985" (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Computer / Human Conversation (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pathological Science – articles (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Pierce, “Technology and Music in the 20th Century” (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Research: artists on “Edwardian Gents and the Arabs” (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Reprint: Pierce, “Ears and Hearing” 1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Reprint: Pierce, “Periodicity and Pitch Perception” 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Studies [assorted articles] (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Essays and a story (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Additional material, Accession ARCH-2004-259
  - Cal Tech visit to Soviet Union 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - NASA Space Committee Research and Development 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Vienna conference (Pierce, "The Contribution of Psychophysics to Music and of Music to Psychophysics") 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical information (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Biographical information (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biographical information ("Miscellaneous, personal, trips and what not" – includes notes from Soviet Union trip of 1973) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Pierce, My Career as an Engineer; An Autobiographical Sketch, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Papers by Pierce (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Papers by Pierce (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Publications 1981 – 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Publications 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Publications 1994-97 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Publications 1998 – 2003 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Publications on J.R. Pierce (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Publications – Fiction (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Publications – Fiction (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Publications – Fiction (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Publications – miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Amazing Stories, October 1934 [does not include anything by Pierce] (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Stories, typescript (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Stories, typescript, "The Blues" (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Stories, typescript, "Tales of the Twelve Teddies" (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Stories, manuscript and typescript (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Stories and verse (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Verse (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Posthumous papers (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - J.R. Pierce bibliography (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "J.R. Pierce Bibliography and much much more, March 26, 1995" (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Pierce, bibliography (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - C.I.T. oral history with J. R. Pierce, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, 1963-1995 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Draper Prize, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous materials (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Awards (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Cal Tech alumni (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence – W. H. Freeman (publisher) 1983-1997 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence – publishers 1981-1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence – Arthur C. Clarke 1988 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence – Andrew Goldstein 1991-92 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence – University of Wyoming (American Heritage Center), 1983-1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, general, 1964, 1981-90 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, general, 1992-2002 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - First phone call off echo (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Echo – photographs 1960-68 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Marconi International Fellowship 1996-97 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Personal correspondence and papers (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Index to Technical Memoranda (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Report on Visit to British electronics laboratories by J. R. Pierce and H. D. Hagstrum, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Transcript of visit with H. G. Wells 1944 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - System Development Foundation, Annual Report, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - International Symposium on Music and Information Science (Japan) 1989 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Northwestern University concert in honor of Pierce 1990 (includes correspondence with Amnon Wolman 1990-91) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Bolinger, Richard, "I Know of No Geometry" (a solo work in five movements written in the Pierce Scale) 1990 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Bauman, Marcia, "Early Computer Sound and Music Synthesis at Bell Telephone Laboratories," Ph.D. thesis, U. of Rochester, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Tribute to Barney Oliver [Bernard M. Oliver] 1995 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Music From Mathematics produced by Bell Telephone Laboratories (LP record with text) 1960 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript musical scores (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - FLOPPY DISK: Opera (Box 7)
  - Japan ‘89, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 7)
  - J.C. Risset / Echo, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 7)
  - Books:
    - The Bell System Technical Journal, 1972. (Box 8)
    - California Institute of Technology. Yearbook, 1933. (Box 8)
    - Friis, Harald T. Seventy-five Years in an Exciting World. (Box 8)
    - IEEE Press. A Century of Honors. (Box 8)
    - IEEE Press. Compendium of Communication and Broadcast Satellites, 1958 to 1980. (Box 8)
    - IRCAM (J.R. Pierce contributor). Passage du XX siecle. (Box 8)
    - National Academy of Engineering (J. R. Pierce contributor). Technology and International Trade. (Box 8)
    - Pierce, John R. Proceedings of the IRE. (Box 8)
    - Pierce, John R. Radio-Electronics. (Box 8)
    - Pierce, John R. and Edward E. David, Jr. Man’s World of Sound. (Box 8)
    - Pierce, John R. and Hiroshi Inose. Information Technology and Civilization. (2 copies) (Box 8)
    - Pierce, J. Almost All About Waves (in Russian). (Box 8)
    - Pierce, John R. An Introduction to Information Theory. (2 copies). (Box 8)
    - Pierce, John R. Quantum Electronics and Waves and Messages. (Box 8)
    - Pierce, John R. and Edward C. Posner. Introduction to Communication Science and Systems. (2 copies). (Box 8)
    - Pierce, John R. and Arthur G. Tressler. The Research State: A History of Science in New Jersey. (Box 8)
  - Books:
    - Pierce, John R. The Science of Musical Sound. (3 copies). (Box 9)
    - Pierce, John R. Telecommunicatie. (Box 9)
    - Pierce, John R. Klank en Muziek. (4 copies). (Box 9)
    - Pierce, John R. and Michael Noll. Signals (2 copies). (Box 9)
    - Pierce, John R. and Michael Noll. Signals (in Spanish, 2 copies). (Box 9)
    - Pierce, John R. Le Son Musical. (Box 9)
    - Pierce, John R. The Science of Musical Sound (in Japanese). (Box 9)
    - Pierce, John R. My Career as an Engineer. (Box 9)
    - Pierce, John R. The Beginnings of a Satellite Communications. (Box 9)
    - Pierce, John R. Science, Art and Communication. (Box 9)
  - Certificates, mounted photographs, and Saturday Evening Post articles (Jan. 14, 1961 on Echo satellite and Nov. 4, 1961 article by Pierce on computers) (Box 10)